<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Projects on exo-cortex: weblog</title><link>https://exo-cortex.github.io/projects/</link><description>Recent content in Projects on exo-cortex: weblog</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 04 Jul 2021 17:02:39 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://exo-cortex.github.io/projects/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>shelf_design_with_python</title><link>https://exo-cortex.github.io/projects/shelf_design_with_python/</link><pubDate>Sun, 04 Jul 2021 17:02:39 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://exo-cortex.github.io/projects/shelf_design_with_python/</guid><description>I wanted to build a large shelf for a while. The shelf should be irregular in its compartment sizes with some of them sticking out more. It shall be really big as to finally store ALL(tm) my stuff that otherwise just lies around all the time.
I began rewriting a python script and put it on github [1]. The script will be updated.
links: [1] shelves_in_python</description></item><item><title>worldbuilding_with_reaction_diffusion_potentials</title><link>https://exo-cortex.github.io/projects/worldbuilding_with_reaction_diffusion_potentials/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jul 2021 20:51:54 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://exo-cortex.github.io/projects/worldbuilding_with_reaction_diffusion_potentials/</guid><description>For at least 5 years I have developed this idea in my head and pondered about ways implement it. Here I will try to at least describe it so that I can at least communicate it.
1. changing the way mass accumulates. &amp;ldquo;Mass tells space-time how to curve, and space-time tells mass how to move.&amp;quot; John Wheeler
In out universe there is a bi-directional relationship between mass and space. Both influence each other: Mass creates a potential $V(x,y,z)$ which is defined for each point in space and the gradient of the potential $\nabla V$ tells us in which direction gravitational pull is moving this mass.</description></item><item><title>wavetable synthesis with images</title><link>https://exo-cortex.github.io/projects/wavetable_synthesis_from_images/</link><pubDate>Wed, 02 Jun 2021 13:43:48 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://exo-cortex.github.io/projects/wavetable_synthesis_from_images/</guid><description>Any sound can become a tone if we repeat it very quickly. The repetition rate becomes the base-frequency of that tone. If we repeat the sample of a basedrum with 1 Hz the base frequency is 1 Hz - well below our hearing range. If we increase the repetition rate to 50 Hz we can actually hear it.
wavetable synthesis works by playing a very short audio sample on repeat. The repetition rate becomes the base frequency.</description></item><item><title>oval_relatives</title><link>https://exo-cortex.github.io/projects/oval_relatives/</link><pubDate>Mon, 31 May 2021 11:15:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://exo-cortex.github.io/projects/oval_relatives/</guid><description>[1] this shape is neither round nor oval. A few years back I experimented with shapes that are almost round, but not quite yet. Slight Imperfections that become irritations are very interesting for me. Imagine a round mirror, or a picture frame shaped like the object [1] above — would you immediately see that it isn&amp;rsquo;t round? Most people would subconsciously expect it to be round or oval and find it to slightly deviate from the norm.</description></item><item><title>reaction_diffusion_systems</title><link>https://exo-cortex.github.io/projects/reaction_diffusion/</link><pubDate>Sun, 30 May 2021 12:46:17 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://exo-cortex.github.io/projects/reaction_diffusion/</guid><description>Reaction-diffusion systems can model many natural pattern-forming processes.
One very popular reaction-diffusion system is the Gray-Scott model, which consists of 2 coupled partial differential equations: $$ \frac{\partial u}{\partial t} = r_u \nabla^2 u - u v ^2 + f(1- u) $$ $$ \frac{\partial v}{\partial t} = r_v \nabla^2 v + u v ^2 - (f + k) v $$
In this model the interaction $u$ and $v$ can be seen as 2 chemicals each with their respective diffusion rates.</description></item><item><title>pitchescurves</title><link>https://exo-cortex.github.io/projects/pitchcurves/</link><pubDate>Wed, 26 May 2021 16:43:45 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://exo-cortex.github.io/projects/pitchcurves/</guid><description>idea: creating sound from pure functions.
The most elemental wave-forms are sine functions.
the pitch of a tone defined over time. Every sound in nature can be deconstructed into a collection of sine functions. A single sine function can only be deconstructed into itself and is therefor called &amp;ldquo;pure&amp;rdquo;.
Some years ago I had the idea of constructing &amp;ldquo;sound emoji&amp;rdquo; - abstract representations of emotions through sound.</description></item></channel></rss>