<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>exo-cortex: weblog</title><link>https://exo-cortex.github.io/</link><description>Recent content on exo-cortex: weblog</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 08 Dec 2022 15:05:38 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://exo-cortex.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>rust libraries</title><link>https://exo-cortex.github.io/how-to/rust-libraries/</link><pubDate>Thu, 08 Dec 2022 15:05:38 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://exo-cortex.github.io/how-to/rust-libraries/</guid><description>Rust libraries I often use As I always seem to forget which library I am using and which version and how they are spelled exactly &amp;hellip; here&amp;rsquo;s a list:
# complex numbers num-complex = &amp;#34;0.4.2&amp;#34; # pseudo-random number generation rand = &amp;#34;0.8.5&amp;#34; # automatically derive arithmetic operations (Add, Sub, etc) for structs derive_more = &amp;#34;0.99.0&amp;#34;</description></item><item><title>scifi_scale</title><link>https://exo-cortex.github.io/blog/scifi_timesscale/</link><pubDate>Thu, 26 May 2022 21:30:11 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://exo-cortex.github.io/blog/scifi_timesscale/</guid><description>A while ago i read some &amp;ldquo;hard&amp;rdquo; science fiction from Charles Stross where he was counting time in kilo-, mega- and gigaseconds. I had to calculate the times each number represented and/or look them up somewhere else in the book. Recently I thought that a nice visualization of these scales might make a good bookmark that people could use.
I added a few time units as well as some extra pieces of information - like the time it takes for light to travel certain distances.</description></item><item><title>blogroll</title><link>https://exo-cortex.github.io/blogroll/blogroll/</link><pubDate>Sat, 08 Jan 2022 12:29:30 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://exo-cortex.github.io/blogroll/blogroll/</guid><description>other cool blogs from friends:
https://effekthasch.org/avs/blog/ this blog from grandchild is documenting the progress of updating/porting the awesome and ancient Winamp-plugin &amp;ldquo;Advanced Visualization Studio&amp;rdquo;. I
https://lindemax.github.io/ here lindeMAX is writing about signal processing math, pcb design, linux and climbing huge mountains. Sometimes about cool new tricks about hugo.
https://music.seba-geek.de/ sebageek started making music with and learning about various music production tools recently. He started a dedicated blog documenting the cool short audio-loops.</description></item><item><title>vintage_yamaha</title><link>https://exo-cortex.github.io/blog/vintage_yamaha/</link><pubDate>Mon, 20 Dec 2021 15:54:03 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://exo-cortex.github.io/blog/vintage_yamaha/</guid><description>love at first sight Last month I bought two quite old pieces of audio equipment from &amp;ldquo;eBay-kleinanzeigen&amp;rdquo;. Admittedly I got interested in the amp, mainly because of its gorgeous design. While reading up on it1 I discovered that it was tremendously well received when Yamaha introduced it in 1981. Back then it cost 1200 DM (~1367 Euros in 20212). As I still like to listen to the radio naturally I needed a nice tuner as well.</description></item><item><title>how to use arduino on linux</title><link>https://exo-cortex.github.io/how-to/arduino/</link><pubDate>Sun, 19 Dec 2021 18:47:23 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://exo-cortex.github.io/how-to/arduino/</guid><description>Installing the arduino IDE goes like this:
$ sudo dnf install arduino On Fedora linux the Arduino appears as a file.
ls -l /dev/ttyACM0 # this returns: # crw-rw----. 1 root dialout 166, 0 Dec 19 18:43 /dev/ttyACM0 This means the &amp;ldquo;file&amp;rdquo; (the file representing the Arduino) is owned by root i.e. only root may manipulate it. In order for your current user to manipulate the Arduino we have to add &amp;ldquo;username&amp;rdquo; to the group &amp;ldquo;dialout&amp;rdquo;:</description></item><item><title>new toy: 7-color e-ink display</title><link>https://exo-cortex.github.io/blog/inky_impressions/</link><pubDate>Mon, 06 Dec 2021 12:03:09 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://exo-cortex.github.io/blog/inky_impressions/</guid><description>After considerable to and fro I finally ordered a 7-color e-ink 1 display for the raspberry pi from pimoroni 2. With the help of the official repository 3 putting images on the the display is quite easy. The repository also has code for other e-ink-displays from pimoroni.
inky impressions display showing a photograph of paris With about 85mm x 115mm it is comparable to typical e-reader display sizes.</description></item><item><title>sed_basics</title><link>https://exo-cortex.github.io/how-to/sed_basics/</link><pubDate>Sat, 30 Oct 2021 12:09:13 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://exo-cortex.github.io/how-to/sed_basics/</guid><description>what is sed? sed is a &amp;ldquo;stream editor&amp;rdquo; in the commandline. It can do a lot of things and I wrote down some basics examples here (to avoid re-googling them in a few months). A great and very thorough guide can be found elsewhere [0]. I only post the most useful examples that I needed so far.
sed typically works by reading an input string, looks for patterns and does something with these patterns.</description></item><item><title>hifiberry_and_mpd_on_raspberry_pi</title><link>https://exo-cortex.github.io/how-to/hifiberry_and_mpd_on_raspberry_pi/</link><pubDate>Sat, 16 Oct 2021 14:45:23 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://exo-cortex.github.io/how-to/hifiberry_and_mpd_on_raspberry_pi/</guid><description>I set up my Raspberry Pi 4 with Arch Linux 1. Having totally forgotten how to make it work with the Hifiberry DAC+ XLR audio shield I had to google, read and understand everything again. In order to avoid this hassle and not waste so much fucking time again (and hopefully help some lost souls on the internet in the process) I&amp;rsquo;m writing everything down here.
enabling the audio-shield For the DAC2-Pro XLR in the &amp;ldquo;/boot/config.</description></item><item><title>new_job / dark matter</title><link>https://exo-cortex.github.io/blog/new_job/</link><pubDate>Thu, 30 Sep 2021 18:18:31 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://exo-cortex.github.io/blog/new_job/</guid><description>Last month I started working at Dark Matter in Berlin. Dark matter is an exhibition space showing various kinetic audiovisual art-pieces conceived by Christopher Bauder. They mostly use special DMX-controlled winches to move glowing light-elements precisely up and down. Collectively the winches create moving and morphing objects in space in sync with musical soundscapes. My favourite pieces there involve precicely moving objects in order to create moving objects that take up space.</description></item><item><title>shelf_design_with_python</title><link>https://exo-cortex.github.io/projects/shelf_design_with_python/</link><pubDate>Sun, 04 Jul 2021 17:02:39 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://exo-cortex.github.io/projects/shelf_design_with_python/</guid><description>I wanted to build a large shelf for a while. The shelf should be irregular in its compartment sizes with some of them sticking out more. It shall be really big as to finally store ALL(tm) my stuff that otherwise just lies around all the time.
I began rewriting a python script and put it on github [1]. The script will be updated.
links: [1] shelves_in_python</description></item><item><title>worldbuilding_with_reaction_diffusion_potentials</title><link>https://exo-cortex.github.io/projects/worldbuilding_with_reaction_diffusion_potentials/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jul 2021 20:51:54 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://exo-cortex.github.io/projects/worldbuilding_with_reaction_diffusion_potentials/</guid><description>For at least 5 years I have developed this idea in my head and pondered about ways implement it. Here I will try to at least describe it so that I can at least communicate it.
1. changing the way mass accumulates. &amp;ldquo;Mass tells space-time how to curve, and space-time tells mass how to move.&amp;quot; John Wheeler
In out universe there is a bi-directional relationship between mass and space. Both influence each other: Mass creates a potential $V(x,y,z)$ which is defined for each point in space and the gradient of the potential $\nabla V$ tells us in which direction gravitational pull is moving this mass.</description></item><item><title>variable density point distributions</title><link>https://exo-cortex.github.io/blog/variable_density_point_distributions/</link><pubDate>Mon, 28 Jun 2021 14:43:57 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://exo-cortex.github.io/blog/variable_density_point_distributions/</guid><description>I finally implemented my own version of the poisson disk sampling algorithm1. The standard algorithm places points on a finite 2D plane with a minimum distance $d_{min}$ between them until there is no more space for additional points. The distribution of the distances of adjacent points is a poisson distribution - hence the name. Robert Bridson described an efficient algorithm to create these samplings2. It uses a grid to store the points in them.</description></item><item><title>scan_local_network_with_nmap</title><link>https://exo-cortex.github.io/how-to/scan_local_network/</link><pubDate>Tue, 22 Jun 2021 14:04:39 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://exo-cortex.github.io/how-to/scan_local_network/</guid><description>You want to find out which devices are available in your local area network - connected to your router. The tool &amp;ldquo;nmap&amp;rdquo; can do this. The command
nmap 192.168.1.0/24 returns exactly that.
I followed the instructions here from the raspberry pi stackexchange</description></item><item><title>easy image manipulation using imagemagick</title><link>https://exo-cortex.github.io/how-to/imagemagick/</link><pubDate>Wed, 02 Jun 2021 16:20:26 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://exo-cortex.github.io/how-to/imagemagick/</guid><description>I often use Imagemagick for simple image-manipulation from the commandline. To use the program run the command &amp;ldquo;convert&amp;rdquo;.
The following is a collection of useful commands for simple image manipulation like resizing, cropping or conversion from one format to another. This collection exists, because I realized that I had to re-google some commands everytime I was using them.
conversion between formats $ convert input_image.png -quality 90 output_image.jpg # or set output format through &amp;#34;-format&amp;#34;-option $ convert input_image.</description></item><item><title>wavetable synthesis with images</title><link>https://exo-cortex.github.io/projects/wavetable_synthesis_from_images/</link><pubDate>Wed, 02 Jun 2021 13:43:48 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://exo-cortex.github.io/projects/wavetable_synthesis_from_images/</guid><description>Any sound can become a tone if we repeat it very quickly. The repetition rate becomes the base-frequency of that tone. If we repeat the sample of a basedrum with 1 Hz the base frequency is 1 Hz - well below our hearing range. If we increase the repetition rate to 50 Hz we can actually hear it.
wavetable synthesis works by playing a very short audio sample on repeat. The repetition rate becomes the base frequency.</description></item><item><title>oval_relatives</title><link>https://exo-cortex.github.io/projects/oval_relatives/</link><pubDate>Mon, 31 May 2021 11:15:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://exo-cortex.github.io/projects/oval_relatives/</guid><description>[1] this shape is neither round nor oval. A few years back I experimented with shapes that are almost round, but not quite yet. Slight Imperfections that become irritations are very interesting for me. Imagine a round mirror, or a picture frame shaped like the object [1] above — would you immediately see that it isn&amp;rsquo;t round? Most people would subconsciously expect it to be round or oval and find it to slightly deviate from the norm.</description></item><item><title>ffmpeg_scripts</title><link>https://exo-cortex.github.io/how-to/ffmpeg_scripts/</link><pubDate>Sun, 30 May 2021 20:09:19 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://exo-cortex.github.io/how-to/ffmpeg_scripts/</guid><description>using ffmpeg. I use ffmpeg to convert videos from one format to the other. In order to create small video files from gifs I use this script:
#!/usr/bin/sh # two-pass video-conversion with resizing to width echo &amp;#34;$1&amp;gt;&amp;gt; $2resizing to width=$3with target video-bitrate of $4&amp;#34; ffmpeg -y -i &amp;#34;$1&amp;#34; -vf scale=$3:-1 -c:v vp9 -preset quality -b:v $4 -pass 1 -an -auto-alt-ref 0 -f webm /dev/null &amp;amp;&amp;amp; \ ffmpeg -i &amp;#34;$1&amp;#34; -vf scale=$3:-1 -c:v vp9 -preset quality -b:v $4 -pass 2 -an -auto-alt-ref 0 $2 explanation -an (no audio) -vf (video filtering -&amp;gt; see below) -c:v (video codec options - e.</description></item><item><title>reaction_diffusion_systems</title><link>https://exo-cortex.github.io/projects/reaction_diffusion/</link><pubDate>Sun, 30 May 2021 12:46:17 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://exo-cortex.github.io/projects/reaction_diffusion/</guid><description>Reaction-diffusion systems can model many natural pattern-forming processes.
One very popular reaction-diffusion system is the Gray-Scott model, which consists of 2 coupled partial differential equations: $$ \frac{\partial u}{\partial t} = r_u \nabla^2 u - u v ^2 + f(1- u) $$ $$ \frac{\partial v}{\partial t} = r_v \nabla^2 v + u v ^2 - (f + k) v $$
In this model the interaction $u$ and $v$ can be seen as 2 chemicals each with their respective diffusion rates.</description></item><item><title>advanced visualization studio</title><link>https://exo-cortex.github.io/blog/advanced_visualization_studio/</link><pubDate>Sun, 30 May 2021 11:35:18 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://exo-cortex.github.io/blog/advanced_visualization_studio/</guid><description>A looooooong time ago in the year 2006 I began to play around with AVS. Advanced Visualization Studio came as a plugin with the famous Winamp Media player. Winamp had 2 plugins that rendered colorful procedural art that reacted to the music. These music visualization plugins were &amp;ldquo;Milkdrop&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;AVS&amp;rdquo;. Typically the user would choose from a variety of presets that would then visualize the sound. But in AVS users could actually create their own presets.</description></item><item><title>rewriting_my_dde_solver</title><link>https://exo-cortex.github.io/blog/rewriting_my_dde_solver/</link><pubDate>Sat, 29 May 2021 20:03:12 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://exo-cortex.github.io/blog/rewriting_my_dde_solver/</guid><description>In the final months of writing my master thesis there was little time. Simultaneously a lot of problems in the c++ code that I had written became very apparent. Since then it has been a dream of me to rewrite the whole thing. Thereby learning even more C++ and also using git/github in a more professional manner (I used it before, but only locally and I didn&amp;rsquo;t quite adhere to a consistent way of commiting changes or wording the commit messages).</description></item><item><title>astrazeneka</title><link>https://exo-cortex.github.io/blog/astrazeneka/</link><pubDate>Sat, 29 May 2021 19:10:14 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://exo-cortex.github.io/blog/astrazeneka/</guid><description>Yesterday I got my vaccine. Finally. Last night and since I&amp;rsquo;ve been feeling quite under the weather. Slight fever, a pumping headache and general drowsiness seems to be part of the general experience. Tomorrow should be better.
update: I got my second dose of vaccination from biontech on 4 august.
update: I got my booster shot (moderna) on 4 january 2022 at the very cool ICC in Berlin.</description></item><item><title>about</title><link>https://exo-cortex.github.io/about/about/</link><pubDate>Sat, 29 May 2021 18:57:06 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://exo-cortex.github.io/about/about/</guid><description>I am a physicist, based in berlin. What I like to work with:
python mathematica c++ blender avs send me an email to [lukipuki at posteo dot net]
All code on this website is licensed under CC0.</description></item><item><title>github first use</title><link>https://exo-cortex.github.io/how-to/github-first-use/</link><pubDate>Fri, 28 May 2021 21:52:50 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://exo-cortex.github.io/how-to/github-first-use/</guid><description>This section shall contain short explanations about git and/or github in my own words. The official man page is often a little dense in information- at least for me.
How to initialize git repository, add files, commit changes and push to existing github repository:
echo &amp;#34;# exo-cortex.github.io&amp;#34; &amp;gt;&amp;gt; README.md git init git add README.md git commit -m &amp;#34;first commit&amp;#34; git branch -M main git remote add origin git@github.com:exo-cortex/exo-cortex.github.io.git git push -u origin main</description></item><item><title>adding math to hugo</title><link>https://exo-cortex.github.io/blog/adding_math_to_hugo/</link><pubDate>Wed, 26 May 2021 18:47:06 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://exo-cortex.github.io/blog/adding_math_to_hugo/</guid><description>with the help of this nice explanation I was able to add math-typesetting to my blog. The framework is KaTeX and it supports a variety of LaTeX math typesetting.
This enables me to write fomulas like these:
$$ z_{i}(t) = (\lambda + i\omega + \gamma |z_{i}(t)|^{2})z_{i}(t) + \sum_{j=0}^{N} \kappa_{i\leftarrow j} e^{i \phi_{i \leftarrow j}}z_{j}(t - \tau_{i\leftarrow j}) $$
It also allows to write math symbols like $\infty$ within text. This is pretty cool for things like $\tfrac{1}{3}$.</description></item><item><title>pitchescurves</title><link>https://exo-cortex.github.io/projects/pitchcurves/</link><pubDate>Wed, 26 May 2021 16:43:45 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://exo-cortex.github.io/projects/pitchcurves/</guid><description>idea: creating sound from pure functions.
The most elemental wave-forms are sine functions.
the pitch of a tone defined over time. Every sound in nature can be deconstructed into a collection of sine functions. A single sine function can only be deconstructed into itself and is therefor called &amp;ldquo;pure&amp;rdquo;.
Some years ago I had the idea of constructing &amp;ldquo;sound emoji&amp;rdquo; - abstract representations of emotions through sound.</description></item></channel></rss>