<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>audio on exo-cortex: weblog</title><link>https://exo-cortex.github.io/tags/audio/</link><description>Recent content in audio on exo-cortex: weblog</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 20 Dec 2021 15:54:03 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://exo-cortex.github.io/tags/audio/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>vintage_yamaha</title><link>https://exo-cortex.github.io/blog/vintage_yamaha/</link><pubDate>Mon, 20 Dec 2021 15:54:03 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://exo-cortex.github.io/blog/vintage_yamaha/</guid><description>love at first sight Last month I bought two quite old pieces of audio equipment from &amp;ldquo;eBay-kleinanzeigen&amp;rdquo;. Admittedly I got interested in the amp, mainly because of its gorgeous design. While reading up on it1 I discovered that it was tremendously well received when Yamaha introduced it in 1981. Back then it cost 1200 DM (~1367 Euros in 20212). As I still like to listen to the radio naturally I needed a nice tuner as well.</description></item><item><title>hifiberry_and_mpd_on_raspberry_pi</title><link>https://exo-cortex.github.io/blog/hifiberry_and_mpd_on_raspberry_pi/</link><pubDate>Sat, 16 Oct 2021 14:45:23 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://exo-cortex.github.io/blog/hifiberry_and_mpd_on_raspberry_pi/</guid><description>I set up my Raspberry Pi 4 with Arch Linux 1. Having totally forgotten how to make it work with the Hifiberry DAC+ XLR audio shield I had to google, read and understand everything again. In order to avoid this hassle and not waste so much fucking time again (and hopefully help some lost souls on the internet in the process) I&amp;rsquo;m writing everything down here.
enabling the audio-shield For the DAC2-Pro XLR in the &amp;ldquo;/boot/config.</description></item><item><title>wavetable synthesis with images</title><link>https://exo-cortex.github.io/blog/wavetable_synthesis_from_images/</link><pubDate>Wed, 02 Jun 2021 13:43:48 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://exo-cortex.github.io/blog/wavetable_synthesis_from_images/</guid><description>Any sound can become a tone if we repeat it very quickly. The repetition rate becomes the base-frequency of that tone. If we repeat the sample of a basedrum with 1 Hz the base frequency is 1 Hz - well below our hearing range. If we increase the repetition rate to 50 Hz we can actually hear it.
wavetable synthesis works by playing a very short audio sample on repeat. The repetition rate becomes the base frequency.</description></item><item><title>pitchescurves</title><link>https://exo-cortex.github.io/blog/pitchcurves/</link><pubDate>Wed, 26 May 2021 16:43:45 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://exo-cortex.github.io/blog/pitchcurves/</guid><description>idea: creating sound from pure functions.
The most elemental wave-forms are sine functions.
the pitch of a tone defined over time. Every sound in nature can be deconstructed into a collection of sine functions. A single sine function can only be deconstructed into itself and is therefor called &amp;ldquo;pure&amp;rdquo;.
Some years ago I had the idea of constructing &amp;ldquo;sound emoji&amp;rdquo; - abstract representations of emotions through sound. The idea was to create short sound of ~1s that can deliver an emotion with the most basic means.</description></item></channel></rss>