<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Blogs on exo-cortex: weblog</title><link>https://exo-cortex.github.io/blog/</link><description>Recent content in Blogs on exo-cortex: weblog</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 30 Sep 2021 18:18:31 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://exo-cortex.github.io/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>new_job / dark matter</title><link>https://exo-cortex.github.io/blog/new_job/</link><pubDate>Thu, 30 Sep 2021 18:18:31 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://exo-cortex.github.io/blog/new_job/</guid><description>Last month I started working at Dark Matter in Berlin. Dark matter is an exhibition space showing various kinetic audiovisual art-pieces conceived by Christopher Bauder. They mostly use special DMX-controlled winches to move glowing light-elements precisely up and down. Collectively the winches create moving and morphing objects in space in sync with musical soundscapes. My favourite pieces there involve precicely moving objects in order to create moving objects that take up space.</description></item><item><title>variable density point distributions</title><link>https://exo-cortex.github.io/blog/variable_density_point_distributions/</link><pubDate>Mon, 28 Jun 2021 14:43:57 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://exo-cortex.github.io/blog/variable_density_point_distributions/</guid><description>I finally implemented my own version of the poisson disk sampling algorithm. The standard algorithm places points on a 2D plane with a minimum distance $d_{min}$ between them until there is no more space for additional points. The distribution of the distances of adjacent points is a poisson distribution - hence the name. Robert Bridson described an efficient algorithm to create these samplings 1. It uses a grid to store the points in them.</description></item><item><title>advanced visualization studio</title><link>https://exo-cortex.github.io/blog/advanced_visualization_studio/</link><pubDate>Sun, 30 May 2021 11:35:18 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://exo-cortex.github.io/blog/advanced_visualization_studio/</guid><description>A looooooong time ago in the year 2006 I began to play around with AVS. Advanced Visualization Studio came as a plugin with the famous Winamp Media player. Winamp had 2 plugins that rendered colorful procedural art that reacted to the music. These music visualization plugins were &amp;ldquo;Milkdrop&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;AVS&amp;rdquo;. Typically the user would choose from a variety of presets that would then visualize the sound. But in AVS users could actually create their own presets.</description></item><item><title>rewriting_my_dde_solver</title><link>https://exo-cortex.github.io/blog/rewriting_my_dde_solver/</link><pubDate>Sat, 29 May 2021 20:03:12 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://exo-cortex.github.io/blog/rewriting_my_dde_solver/</guid><description>In the final months of writing my master thesis there was little time. Simultaneously a lot of problems in the c++ code that I had written became very apparent. Since then it has been a dream of me to rewrite the whole thing. Thereby learning even more C++ and also using git/github in a more professional manner (I used it before, but only locally and I didn&amp;rsquo;t quite adhere to a consistent way of commiting changes or wording the commit messages).</description></item><item><title>astrazeneka</title><link>https://exo-cortex.github.io/blog/astrazeneka/</link><pubDate>Sat, 29 May 2021 19:10:14 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://exo-cortex.github.io/blog/astrazeneka/</guid><description>Yesterday I got my vaccine. Finally. Last night and since I&amp;rsquo;ve been feeling quite under the weather. Slight fever, a pumping headache and general drowsiness seems to be part of the general experience. Tomorrow should be better.</description></item><item><title>adding math to hugo</title><link>https://exo-cortex.github.io/blog/adding_math_to_hugo/</link><pubDate>Wed, 26 May 2021 18:47:06 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://exo-cortex.github.io/blog/adding_math_to_hugo/</guid><description>with the help of this nice explanation I was able to add math-typesetting to my blog. The framework is KaTeX and it supports a variety of LaTeX math typesetting.
This enables me to write fomulas like these:
$$ z_{i}(t) = (\lambda + i\omega + \gamma |z_{i}(t)|^{2})z_{i}(t) + \sum_{j=0}^{N} \kappa_{i\leftarrow j} e^{i \phi_{i \leftarrow j}}z_{j}(t - \tau_{i\leftarrow j}) $$
It also allows to write math symbols like $\infty$ within text. This is pretty cool for things like $\tfrac{1}{3}$.</description></item></channel></rss>